<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<<<<<<< HEAD
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Iqbal A. Comics</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Vine</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/blog/the-vine</link><description>&lt;h1&gt;The Vine&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short story/short comic about a huge vine that connects Earth to the moon! Goddammit, can that ever happen?!?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not, but it is only a story, I guess...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*nwCwexJwgn7cT74llzOfHw.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*wuz9ECQnmbLl6Or_Igm15A.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*9Ccj0_smdBD8MA4cT_HHoQ.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*T0uWXfAvYE3uz07B7N5k1g.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*dV2cqic58THFafA9djbaqg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*_P1qvBRIgNcqX3mhknWZyw.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*P5IZcK-3mWGGEma1AE11kQ.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*fO_NqpyO-n2pl0Q_m3l4-Q.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal Ali</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2018-10-06:blog/the-vine</guid><category>comics</category></item><item><title>Illustrator lettering process</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/blog/illustrator-lettering-process</link><description>&lt;h1&gt;Illustrator lettering process&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while ago I took this comic book lettering course by John Roshell, over at Lynda.com. It’s a fantastic course and I recommend this to anyone interested in lettering their own comic books or graphic novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst many of the valuable insights, one which stayed with me long after taking this course is the process of speech ballooning. It occurred to me that this wasn’t documented anywhere else on the internet (that I’ve found anyway), so I thought I’d document it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The speech balloons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what I’m talking about…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*97GErgHPQd4oVn4-Gpj8hg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty straight forward right? Here are the steps you’d normally take if you were doing it the “classic” way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Create an ellipse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2060/1*tB9W-iwdbxzLW9uNKEvqDg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Square it off using the anchor points, give it a white fill and a stroke that’s appropriate for your book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Add your text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2028/1*5G43Nv4x4SrOLsXFcVdsMw.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to resize your ellipse accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Add your tail&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2024/1*9GlgmHasdOwGJU0Us2XLFw.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draw your tail with the pen tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Merge the shapes together&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that, you’ll need to select &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; the ellipse and the tail, then with the pathfinder (&lt;em&gt;Window &amp;gt; Pathfinder&lt;/em&gt;), you need to select “Unite”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*7Y0urGxF_4v02W-E-eD_Vw.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After uniting, you’ll get you’ll get your final word balloon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*97GErgHPQd4oVn4-Gpj8hg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problem with this last step&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this method works and seemingly very popular, there are some drawbacks with this method. Notably, once united, the word balloon is a single shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to update the words in the balloon, it’s difficult and you may need to recreate the balloon almost from scratch. Also, with this method you’ll pretty much need to create balloons each time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’d be great to be able to retain the separate shapes, yet still have the balloon properly formed as above, so you’re able to edit this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following approach does just that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, here’s the basic concept:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*A_spEYPcKDUjjbs_9ZW8Rg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking these one by one…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have an ellipse as before, but this time there’s no stroke on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tail, which has the stroke and the fill on it, as per usual&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A duplicate of the bubble from point 1. this time with the stroke (you either want to make this extra thick or apply the stroke to only the outside of the shape)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that you have these three parts either arranged in this order or on separate layers. So the top layer would contain balloon from 1., the bottom layer contains the balloon from 3., and the tail is sandwiched inbetween.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you have in the end is something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*-lG8lpLVJYztjW_4Zh66eQ.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See? All the shapes are separate, and thus totally editable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to resize the balloon, just make sure you select the shapes from both 1. and 3. only and resize away! As long as you select points from both the ellipse layers, you’ll find that the stroke remains consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can even take multiple balloons and merge them together like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2504/1*RNd5qZIxhE3qLicCozdcQA.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the objects above are separate, so each are editable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Layers or arranged objects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can either have 1., 2., and 3. on separate layers &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; you can have them all on the same layer and arrange them in the order you need. What you choose is up to you. One advantage of using separate layers is that you don’t need to keep arranging&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the layers I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*sbW_2_x5w10CoX0RlIrH1g.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you found this article useful. If you did, then please consider following me on &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/midfrenzy"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.tumblr.com"&gt;tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and drop me a message. If I’ve got anything wrong, or if you have a better alternative to improve my process, then please also let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Iqbal Ali, I write comics among other things. You can check out my work on &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.com"&gt;midlfrenzy.com&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href="http://goo.gl/Y1cTro"&gt;Amazon page can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal A.</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2016-10-05:blog/illustrator-lettering-process</guid><category>tutorial</category><category>development</category></item><item><title>My comic book production “build” process</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/blog/my-comic-book-production-build-process</link><description>&lt;h1&gt;My comic book production “build” process&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the scene. You’ve got your finished “lettered” comic book pages. You’ve got your cover, your internal title and credit pages. Now you’ve built/exported a multitude of files ready to use in various ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a lower quality digital file for sharing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a high quality digital file to send some digital publishing sites&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;separate jpg files to share on social media and host on your site as a web-comic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a high quality print file, with the correct gutters and bleeds to get your book printed. Your print file also has some additional blank pages to ensure easier flow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this, you had to do manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then you spotted a minor error. Damn. No problem. You fix it, then do the exports all over again. But then you spot something else, then something else. Now this is getting annoying…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, by far, the worst part of the comic book production process is this exporting to multiple formats and files, ready to get published. It’s laborious, boring, time consuming and frustrating — at least it is for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that though, it’s fine if you’re only working on a couple of books. But what if you’re working on a lot of books? Or have a lot of projects you’ve built previously but now need to export again for some reason?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hit this problem quite recently. As a self-published author I’m constantly learning and tweaking previous work. Even for new projects, I find myself going through endless build cycles until I get the exports “just right”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed to automate my comic book production. I wanted to make that part of the job easier, more consistent, and more enjoyable. I also wanted to be able to add a new book format (like epub or kindle) when I wanted to, without adding too much overhead to by production time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With those things in mind, I’ve created a script to help me do just that! This script automates my entire production process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if I wanted to make an edit to a page or two, I’d make those edits, save the file, run my script and would get all my exports at a touch of a button. Since it’s automated, I’ve reduced the risk of human error in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My file exports&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I work is that I have a specific&lt;strong&gt; “publish”&lt;/strong&gt; folder defined on my desktop. In that folder, I have a separate folder per project. The following image is the project folder for my graphic novel &lt;strong&gt;“Strange Skies”&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*sCfKoe8eVKR6b8OFUvLi4A.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strange Skies is a 160 page graphic novel, so there’s a lot of pages to export if I had to do this manually. These are all the exports I &lt;em&gt;currently&lt;/em&gt; need (I’m hoping to add epub and kindle formats soon).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I export…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a high quality 160 page digital pdf for publishing to ComiXology, Comichaus etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Strange-Skies.digi-hi.pdf" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*fQb6UkiO70PbQS2fIXhVow.png" /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strange-Skies.digi-hi.pdf&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a low quality digital pdf (for sharing) — no screenshot required as it’s just a lower quality version of the above…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a .CBZ file which I might make available for torrenting (yes, I’m considering this as an option) — not sure how to present this to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a JPG folder of all the pages of my book with the outer white margins &lt;strong&gt;cropped&lt;/strong&gt; to make the most efficient use of space…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="See? No white margins!" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*kvAc9fuj1JggHVjGxFuxBw.png" /&gt;&lt;em&gt;See? No white margins!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a print-ready file with the correct bleed and gutters (I use CreateSpace for my printing) — as you can see below, there’s added gutter spaces on the left for odd-numbered pages and on the right for even numbered pages…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2796/1*dglGPMu2XpwKEwlgazuwBQ.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a print-ready cover file along with the back cover and spine:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/4036/1*S__ws991rbadb7GAKnrwAw.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a cover file for the front cover isolated from the spine and back blurb (this is needed as places like ComiXology want a separate cover file to feature on search results etc.) — it’s also just useful to have as a separate file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2092/1*YzqJ9CYr36yl2XIydP2G1w.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Source files&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are my source files? Well they consist of…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A number of Illustrator files with the lettering. The images for the pages are linked to separate TIFF files. I have about ten artboards per Illustrator file with a page per artboard…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*_8-tr4r3CEyYtRExUF8geg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One cover file for printing. This cover file contains the front, spine and back cover.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*wPGD0klgS7CIdKo6eLjkDA.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My script runs through the illustrator files and exports the necessary pdfs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also takes the cover, and extracts the front cover as a separate file. All of this is done automatically when I run the script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, is this something you might find useful, or is it just me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just in case, I’ve made the &lt;a href="https://github.com/iqbalali/publisher"&gt;script available on github&lt;/a&gt; for you to download and use for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll be explaining in detail how to use it in subsequent posts. I’ll do this in my own time, however if there is a sufficient interest, I’ll make it a higher priority to document the process — I’m just not sure how many will find this useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m assuming not many…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I could be wrong, so if you think this is something you’d find useful, then please let me know and I’ll write up those posts asap for you! You can message me on &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/midfrenzy"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.tumblr.com"&gt;tumblr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Iqbal Ali, I write comics among other things. You can check out my work on &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.com"&gt;mildfrenzy.com&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href="http://goo.gl/Y1cTro"&gt;Amazon page can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal A.</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2016-10-05:blog/my-comic-book-production-build-process</guid><category>tutorial</category></item><item><title>Productivity hacks that worked for me</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/blog/productivity-hacks-that-worked-for-me</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to find ways of increasing my productivity lately as I felt it was waning. And so I thought back to the time when I felt I reached the peak of my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I experimented with every technique I came across in an effort to &lt;strong&gt;just get stuff done&lt;/strong&gt;. My goal was to create a graphic novel and I didn’t want it to take years to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these hacks are techniques, some are principles. This post is a way of documenting the process for my benefit, but hopefully it’s also useful for you too, whatever your goal might be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here goes…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ignore milestones, instead focus on mini-goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is as much of a mindset shift as much as a principle and is something I picked up from &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Focus-power-targeted-thinking-more/dp/027373461X/"&gt;Jurgen Wolf’s excellent book: **“Focus: The power of targeted thinking”&lt;/a&gt;**.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In it he mentions that setting a milestone date for your end goal is a big motivation killer as milestones are rarely achievable. Instead, he advises breaking down your goal into pieces. These become your small and achievable “mini-goals”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on achieving those one at a time and you’ll get the rewarding feeling of achieving something regularly. This gives your motivation a boost and hence makes you feel more productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It then becomes easier to develop a habit of working on your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are examples of some of &lt;strong&gt;my&lt;/strong&gt; mini-goals. My graphic novel was broken into scenes (the story was already written)…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mini-goal #1:&lt;/strong&gt; Draw the scene as rough comic pages (thumbnails)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mini-goal #2: &lt;/strong&gt;Pencil one page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mini-goal #3: &lt;/strong&gt;Ink one page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of those goals is small enough to be achievable but substantial enough to be meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without breaking down my goal like this, finishing a graphic novel would seem a herculean task. The simple act of focusing on an immediately achievable goal without concerning myself with the end goal allowed me to focus more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So are milestones completely worthless?&lt;/strong&gt; Well, not quite. I used to set myself &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;targets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of finishing six pages per week. These were like weekly milestones. Also, my major milestone became more of a projection than a fixed deadline I had to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pareto principle (aka. the 80/20 rule)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle states that “80% of your output comes from 20% of your work”. In other words, only 20% of what you do is truly productive for a particular goal or set of goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To identify this productive 20%, I started each day listing down all the tasks I needed to accomplish. This list included &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; I needed to do, not just tasks related to my project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then categorised these tasks as…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High impact&lt;/strong&gt; — this has a great immediate impact on hitting my end goal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium impact&lt;/strong&gt; — these are tasks I needed to do but which didn’t directly relate to my finished product&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low impact &lt;/strong&gt;— these are tasks which might have benefits further down the line, but the immediate impact is negligible&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then knew what were the most valuable tasks to do each day. That is, I’d pick off the high impact tasks, before picking up the low impact. For maximum productivity, I needed to do as many high impact tasks as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jurgen’s book, he also advises what to do with low priority tasks, for example hiring a virtual assistant to do those tasks for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtual assistants don’t cost too much on Upwork or fiverr, but it’s up to you to decide whether it is a worthwhile investment to offload low priority tasks, allowing you to pick up more high impact tasks per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another benefit of categorising your tasks is you can identify ways of maximising the delivery of high impact tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, I discovered that I spent a long time laying out finished pages in the desktop publishing software I was using. I needed to export the pages so I could review them. This task kept coming up on my daily list a LOT and it was a real drain as it was a manual task which was always the same. It was a real chore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this was a high impact task, it was worth me taking the time to create some scripts to automate this part of my process and help improve my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(In case you’re interested, you can &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@iqbalali/my-comic-book-production-build-process-e8f5090731c7"&gt;find out more about this here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@iqbalali/my-comic-book-production-build-process-e8f5090731c7"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My comic book production “build” process&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Imagine the scene. You’ve got your finished “lettered” comic book pages. You’ve got your cover, your internal title and…&lt;/em&gt;medium.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can’t code, consider hiring someone to do this for you — it’s worth it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pomodoro Technique&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a technique where you set a timer for (traditionally) twenty-five minutes. During each “Pomodoro” you focus on a specific task or set of tasks, eliminating all other distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After each Pomodoro, you take a five-minute break, before repeating again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have fond memories of &lt;a href="undefined"&gt;tom britton&lt;/a&gt; and I do this at my house. We’d start by preparing the tasks we wanted to focus on, organising them so they can be achieved in the time limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my comic book work, I aimed to do at least two pomodoros a day. I also employed Spotify’s &lt;strong&gt;Deep Focus&lt;/strong&gt; playlist to help me focus during this pomodoro. Brain.fm is also a good choice for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s something about putting some headphones on and losing oneself in the specially designed musical landscapes which allow you to switch off from the outside world and focus on the job at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that these pomodoros were especially effective because I had done the work beforehand by creating my task lists and identifying my high impact tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chain calendar&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above techniques and principles were fine and dandy, and when I was working I was definitely more productive. However, bringing myself round to start work each and every day was still tough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to the “chain calendar” habit-forming technique developed by Jerry Seinfeld — I think he created it, but don’t quote me on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that you print out a calendar and hang it on the wall. And then for each day you work on your project, you put a cross on a respective day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is simple: &lt;em&gt;don’t break the chain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think my record was thirty-five days without breaking the chain. It’s probably not the greatest record, but it was useful to get me into a habit of working regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, I didn’t even need the calendar. Working on my project just became something I did. It became an everyday habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is by no means the optimal process for productivity, but for me, it was a really great start. I used this process for most of the books I’ve worked on, and I can comfortably say that it had a big impact on me and my productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this will work for you, maybe not. But I think it’s worth just getting started with a process and tweak and optimise it in order to get the most out of your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck with all your work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Iqbal Ali, I write comics among other things. You can check out my work on &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.com"&gt;mildfrenzy.com&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href="http://goo.gl/Y1cTro"&gt;Amazon page can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal A.</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2016-10-05:blog/productivity-hacks-that-worked-for-me</guid><category>tutorial</category></item><item><title>Self-publishing graphic novels with CreateSpace — Part 1</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/blog/self-publishing-graphic-novels-with-createspace-part-1</link><description>&lt;p&gt;CreateSpace is a free self-publishing print-on-demand service/platform. It’s also Amazon owned so the experience of making your book(s) available for sale worldwide through Amazon is effortless if you use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard about CreateSpace, you can &lt;a href="https://www.createspace.com/"&gt;find out more here&lt;/a&gt;. Needless to say, being able to self-publish graphic novels, making the printed versions available worldwide is a game-changer for indie creators!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said all that, while it is a godsend for indie publishers, it does come with a learning curve as there’s not many guides to cover publishing of graphic novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But fear not, I’ll be writing articles covering everything I’ve learned about the subject in a series of posts! Starting with this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part is about deciding on the print dimensions and preparing templates for artwork. This is important as you don’t want to get too far down the line of creating your artwork and finishing your lettering only to discover that you’ve used the wrong dimensions — I’ve made this mistake, and it’s painful...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warning! If you decide to use this as a process, please bare in mind that everything I do is work in progress. These guidelines and templates are a good starting point, but test everything out yourself to make sure it works for you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Artwork templates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, let’s get straight into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A US comic book is &lt;strong&gt;6.625 inches&lt;/strong&gt; wide by &lt;strong&gt;10.25 inches&lt;/strong&gt; high. The closest equivalent size in CreateSpace is &lt;strong&gt;7 inches&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;10 inches&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing graphic novels, you could actually use any size you want, but I like sticking to standards where I can unless there’s a good reason not to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, &lt;strong&gt;7 inches&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;10 inches&lt;/strong&gt; seems close enough to the traditional size. But since graphic novels tend to have images bleeding to the edge of the page, we really need to make sure we’re clear what size we’re working to so that the artwork has enough bleed to fit and that we don’t lose too much artwork when the pages get trimmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, it was important to find the right balance between the two formats so I could easily switch between the two without much pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My template&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve arrived at my template after much trial and error. It’s tailored to fit my production method which is based on scripts which run and “publish” my pages ready for printing. This is so I don’t need to use programs like InDesign at all in my process. I’ll go over this process in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can, of course, still use this template even if you’re not running automated scripts like myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first assumption with this template is that all my projects will have images bleeding to the edge of the page. In reality, many books that I’ve published don’t need to go to the edges, but I find it easier to work on this assumption as it helps me create those aforementioned automation scripts. It also keeps things nice and easy for my production process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned previously (but I wanted reiterate it here): the template I use is a mash up of both aforementioned sizes. So while I publish in CreateSpace now, I could in future decide to publish in the more “traditional” US format without much hassle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, below is the template I’ve started using for all my artwork. This is the template I send to all artists I work with, so there are no “surprises” when I get pages back for the production process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comic artwork template" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*4arx-Euf240KECSlb9x4Ag.png" /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comic artwork template&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry if you’re lost, I’ll walk you through it from the centre out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Live area&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All panel borders, important artwork and lettering will go inside the live area. Any artwork &lt;em&gt;outside &lt;/em&gt;this area, i.e. in the bleed, could get cropped in the final print. If you visit the &lt;a href="https://www.createspace.com/Products/Book/InteriorPDF.jsp"&gt;CreateSpace page on the subject&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see a guide to what the live area should be depending on the number of pages that your book has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually have page counts up to 200 pages, and I found the live region in my template to be fine for my purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*pc36YAqWWfLr1t3kcZ4-CA.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bleed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, artwork in this area could be subject to cropping and the actual trim size of the comic will be &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt; within this region. The blue boundary is the closest approximation of the CreateSpace trim size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t be fooled into thinking that the final book trim from CreateSpace will be consistent from book to book. Pages “slip” as they zoom through the printers. This means there is often a big difference in what ends up as the final page from book to book and page to page. So to reiterate this again, the crop would be &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt; in the bleed area but the blue borders is a very rough approximation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you include the thick blue lines at the top and bottom of the page as the bleed, you’ll get the US comic size so. As we’re interested in CreateSpace publishing, these two blue borders will be the first casualty as we‘ll be cropping those before sending the final PDF to the printing press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: An artist should apply artwork over the entire page (yes, that includes over the blue bands at the top and bottom of the page). It’s good to keep yourself open to the US format should you choose it later.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to use this template?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do decide to use this template, you should download or copy the image directly from the browser, open up in Photoshop and resize it. You also need to bump up the resolution to 300dpi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the image size settings I use (In Photoshop: &lt;em&gt;Image &amp;gt; Image Size&lt;/em&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*zkztZlX06G3oHHV7VynmAQ.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that I’ve oversized the image. It’s a good idea to do your artwork on an oversized canvas to retain as much quality as possible before you shrink it down. This is especially the case if you use this template as you might need to shrink the pages to slightly different dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your computer is too slow to go to &lt;strong&gt;14 inches&lt;/strong&gt; wide, then go to at least &lt;strong&gt;10 inches&lt;/strong&gt; wide instead. But &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; work on the exact page size. Always go slightly larger — that’s my opinion anyway. Other views do exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lettering and production&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the artwork is finished and you’re ready to letter or resize the page for printing, you’ll resize the image to &lt;strong&gt;7 inches&lt;/strong&gt; width, by &lt;strong&gt;10.565 inches&lt;/strong&gt; height. If you’ve kept to 300dpi for your artwork, your final image size in pixels would be &lt;strong&gt;2100 px &lt;/strong&gt;width by&lt;strong&gt; 3170 px &lt;/strong&gt;height. This is perfect for ComiXology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side note:&lt;/strong&gt; When resizing the image, remember to avoid the JPG format! It’s lossy, which means that each time you save, you lose valuable information from the image. This is bad and will cause you problems, especially if you want your comic published to ComiXology! I always remind my artists to avoid JPG at all stages of the artworking process unless it’s to send images to me to review.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stick to TIFF format instead.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you have an image that is sized to &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10.565 inches&lt;/strong&gt;, however as discussed earlier, that includes those blue areas on the top and bottom of the page. Since we’re publishing to CreateSpace, we don’t need those areas, meaning the final dimensions will be &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10.25 inches&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s more to discuss on this subject, but I think I’ve covered what I wanted to in this part. In this article I wanted to outline the method I use to ensure my artwork is produced in the correct format and with the right dimensions with CreateSpace publishing in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@iqbalali/self-publishing-graphic-novels-with-createspace-part-2-ce082778558e"&gt;next part&lt;/a&gt;, I’ll describe how I resize the pages properly and ensure I have the right sizes with the correct amount of bleed. Getting this wrong means you’ll have your pages rejected by CreateSpace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while you’re here, if you found this useful, please consider following me on &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/midfrenzy"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.tumblr.com"&gt;tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and drop me a message. If I’ve got anything wrong, or if you have a better alternative, then please also let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Iqbal Ali, I write comics among other things. You can check out my work on &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.com"&gt;midlfrenzy.com&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href="http://goo.gl/Y1cTro"&gt;Amazon page can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal A.</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2016-10-05:blog/self-publishing-graphic-novels-with-createspace-part-1</guid><category>publishing</category><category>tutorial</category></item><item><title>Self-publishing graphic novels with CreateSpace — Part 2</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/blog/self-publishing-graphic-novels-with-createspace-part-2</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This guide continues from my last post, which detailed how to set up your pages ready for printing through CreateSpace. If you haven’t read that article yet, I recommend that you do as this post continues directly from that one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick recap of that previous article…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I established that I want to publish to CreateSpace and the final book dimensions will be &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10 inches&lt;/strong&gt;. I shared my template with you and had images which could resized to &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10.565 inches.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I’ll describe my process for getting the final pages ready for production and how to create PDFs that CreateSpace won’t reject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Here comes Illustrator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Illustrator for lettering my comics. However, there are alternatives available. For example, there’s &lt;a href="https://affinity.serif.com/en-gb/"&gt;Affinity Designer&lt;/a&gt; which is an awesome application, though it just falls short for my process (I have a very particular process where steps are automated by scripts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could also letter in Photoshop or Clip Studio or any other application that you’re comfortable lettering in. It really doesn’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is about my process and I personally letter and produce in Illustrator, and start with a artboards sized to &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10.25 inches&lt;/strong&gt;. I’ll tell you why this needs to be specifically this size in a moment. But first I wanted to finish my tour of my Illustrator process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, I place my &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10.565 inches &lt;/strong&gt;image onto each artboard. I make sure the image fits on the board perfectly in terms of the width. In terms of the height, I’ll be losing parts of the top and the bottom of image outside the board. These are the blue shaded areas I described in the last post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Losing those parts of the image is not a problem. Remember, that why we artwork with the extra bleed in mind. All the final lettering is done with a keen awareness as to where the “Live area” of the page is (&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@iqbalali/self-publishing-graphic-novels-with-createspace-part-1-96f33485eb08"&gt;you really do need to read my last article if you have no idea what I’m talking about&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Back to CreateSpace&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10.25 inches &lt;/strong&gt;when the final printed book will be &lt;strong&gt;7 inches x 10 inches&lt;/strong&gt;? Well, because we want our artwork to bleed to the edges, and the &lt;a href="https://www.createspace.com/Products/Book/InteriorPDF.jsp"&gt;CreateSpace’s page on the subject&lt;/a&gt; tells us the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want your images to bleed to the edges of your book, ensure that they extend at least .125" beyond the final trim size from the top, bottom and outer edges and submit your PDF .25" higher and .125" wider than your selected trim size to accommodate the full bleed area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, the first time you read that, it made little sense. The following image should make visualising what they’re saying a little easier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*GHZhsoAfoMrPGQH0UWiX3Q.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above image shows a double page spread &lt;strong&gt;and is not to any sort of scale&lt;/strong&gt;. The left is an “even” numbered page and the right is an “odd” numbered page. The dotted line represents the where the pages bind. The area shaded blue is a &lt;strong&gt;0.125 inch&lt;/strong&gt; bleed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, for an &lt;strong&gt;even&lt;/strong&gt; numbered page, you have a bleed on the top, bottom and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;left&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; of the page (the &lt;em&gt;outer&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;edges&lt;/em&gt;). There is &lt;strong&gt;no bleed&lt;/strong&gt; on the right where the page binding is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For odd numbered pages, the bleed is on the top, bottom and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, but not on the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So just to remind you that my final page is &lt;strong&gt;10.25 inches &lt;/strong&gt;high, whereas the final printed height is&lt;strong&gt; 10 inches&lt;/strong&gt;. This means I’ve added a total of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;0.25 inches&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to the height of the final page. That’s made up of a 0.125 inches on the top &lt;strong&gt;PLUS &lt;/strong&gt;0.125 inches of the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;haven’t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; added anything to the width. The size I work on is &lt;strong&gt;7 inches&lt;/strong&gt; and the final width of the book is also &lt;strong&gt;7 inches&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is that? Well that’s because you lose some space where the pages bind together. That page surface is “lost” and we call this the &lt;strong&gt;gutter&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what this approximately looks like (again, don’t expect any sort of accurate scaling on this):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*Jne-6Zi9tFf35i1MDHVHHQ.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grey shaded area shows the gutter. That part of the page is lost in the binding of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s read the CreateSpace paragraph on the subject again, this time taking into account the last last part of the last sentence only:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… submit your PDF .25" higher and .125" wider than your selected trim size to accommodate the full bleed area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So basically, if we want a &lt;strong&gt;7 inch&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;10 inch&lt;/strong&gt; book, we need our PDF to have dimensions of &lt;strong&gt;7.125 inches &lt;/strong&gt;by&lt;strong&gt; 10.25 inches&lt;/strong&gt;. This will ensure we have a perfect PDF from a CreateSpace perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have the correct height. We just need to add 0.125 inches of space for the gutters (on the right for even numbered pages, and to the left for all odd numbered pages).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to do in a program like InDesign , go to &lt;em&gt;File &amp;gt; New&amp;gt; Document&lt;/em&gt;, just make a new document with the following settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*4fztvCkY-0sXpTTVsWmUog.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve converted my units to millimeters as InDesign seems to use this by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that in the Bleed and Slug section that the inside bleed is set to 0 and the rest is &lt;strong&gt;3.175 mm (0.125 inches)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*_anyemwRBtT8YeGh82tDyA.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that you need to click on the link icon on the right to allow you to set these separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternative to using InDesign, you can do this manually for each of your files — i.e. you can just add 0.125 inch space for each of your pages manually. I don’t recommend this option as it can be frustrating, time consuming and, in my opinion, just a waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can’t get hold of InDesign, then check out this &lt;a href="https://onextrapixel.com/10-best-alternatives-to-adobe-indesign/"&gt;list of alternative desktop publishing applications&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above felt like too much work for me — I hate using these applications. So this is where I automate! I write scripts which automatically processes all my Illustrator files and adds the required gutter spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I do think this is where I might lose most of you as things do get pretty “techy”, therefore I’ll save this for a different article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, just to finish this guide off, remember when you upload your interior file to CreateSpace, select the bleed option:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*RAIZ_q1pGQ7u9p2PGJ4vYg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set up of books in CreateSpace using the online form is actually really simple once your file is set up correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you found this article useful. If you did, then please consider following me on &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/midfrenzy"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.tumblr.com"&gt;tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and drop me a message. If I’ve got anything wrong, or if you have a better alternative to improve my process, then please also let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Iqbal Ali, I write comics among other things. You can check out my work on &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.com"&gt;midlfrenzy.com&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href="http://goo.gl/Y1cTro"&gt;Amazon page can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal Ali</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2016-10-05:blog/self-publishing-graphic-novels-with-createspace-part-2</guid><category>tutorial</category></item><item><title>What it’s like to be completely out of your depth</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/blog/strange-skies-afterwards</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote the following as an afterward for my first graphic novel: Strange Skies. I since realised that perhaps it’s worth publishing separately here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here’s the article, I hope it helps with anyone else in the same position. It’s exhausting, but such a great place to be!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, I was in the park with my son. He was around two at the time. I had developed RSI from writing and drawing. I was sleep deprived and exhausted. I think my son had only recently started sleeping properly, and, by then, my sleep patterns had become messed up. Added to this, I had stopped doing any sort of exercise, so I was in really bad shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, while I was out there, I remember thinking about the book I was working on: Strange Skies. I was halfway through the project and wondered what the heck I had gotten myself into. It was my first ever comic over four pages in length, and it was a full-blown 165-page graphic novel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, around two and a half years previous to that moment, I had decided to throw myself into the project. I could have picked something shorter, but there was something about this story that really drove me. The themes of journeys and destinations (or lack thereof) seemed appropriate to that transitionary period of my life. I was about to become a father and was about to quit full-time work in order to concentrate on my writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, flash forward to that moment in the park, where I had just finished page eighty (or thereabouts). And the analogy of the light at the end of the tunnel popped into my head. That light seemed far away, and I was getting impatient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what was I going to do? I couldn’t exactly leave the tunnel, could I? I couldn’t dig myself out into the middle of nowhere, miles from home and from my destination. I was a different person from when I started. More specifically, I was halfway to becoming a different person. I had sacrificed so much to get this far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(By the way, “home” in this analogy is the blissful ignorance of how hard it was to create a graphic novel and the relative luxury of staying within my comfort zone. The “destination” is the pride I imagined of holding the finished book in my hands.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I decided I had no choice but to continue with the book. So I persevered. But I’ll be honest, I rushed it. I was so busy concentrating on reaching the light as quickly as possible that I had sacrificed quality along the way. I thought my journey would end upon reaching the light. I thought that creating a graphic novel was all about the destination. All about having that final book in my hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating these books, and telling stories, is all about the journey. It’s all about being in that tunnel, writing the stories and enjoying the privilege of being allowed here in the first place — there’s a strict requirements policy for entry into the tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this leads me to tell you about the book you’re holding: the second edition of Strange Skies. This is an edition in which I’ve rejigged the words and the artwork — well, technically Stephen Baskerville rejigged the artwork by re-inking it, but you get what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, I thought it was important to get this book “right.” I’m now six books into my career, and reading the original version left me cold and embarrassed. So I put into practice the now couple of years of writing experience I had to really be true to the original vision I had for the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’d be lying if I said I was completely content with this latest product. I don’t think I ever could be satisfied with a book I’ve done. But what I can tell you is what this book now means to me. This book was a challenge I set myself. A challenge I mistakenly thought was a marathon but was instead an eternal treadmill (a fun eternal treadmill, at that). Strange Skies is the book that started me on the journey as a writer. A journey with no particular destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not having that destination is something I’m really okay with now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you found this article useful. If you did, then please consider following me on &lt;a href="http://www.twitter.com/midfrenzy"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.tumblr.com"&gt;tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and drop me a message. If I’ve got anything wrong, or if you have a better alternative to improve my process, then please also let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Iqbal Ali, I write comics among other things. You can check out my work on &lt;a href="http://www.mildfrenzy.com"&gt;midlfrenzy.com&lt;/a&gt;. My &lt;a href="http://goo.gl/Y1cTro"&gt;Amazon page can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal A.</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2016-10-05:blog/strange-skies-afterwards</guid><category>tutorial</category></item><item><title>Aya-20</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/promo/aya-20</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal Ali</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2012 14:01:01 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2012-03-02:promo/aya-20</guid></item><item><title>Aya-30</title><link>http://www.iqbala.com/promo/aya-30</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal Ali</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2012 14:01:01 +0000</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.iqbala.com,2012-03-02:promo/aya-30</guid></item></channel></rss>
=======
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Sitespect Documentation</title><link>/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Counting users into an experiment</title><link>/2016/counting-users-into-an-experiment</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This post assumes you've got some familiarity with SiteSpect already. What I'll be covering are the key concepts of "counting" users into a test so you can better control when you're counting people into an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A simple example of "counted"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a simple example test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to create a test where we want to change the button text on the homepage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="homepage control" src="/img/homepage-control.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to change "Get times &amp;amp; tickets" to read "Search" instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so simple. You create a factor where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trigger:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URL: Regex to match the homepage URL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Body: Regex to match "Get times &amp;amp; tickets"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search: Regex to match "Get times &amp;amp; tickets"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace: Replacement button text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now before you pat yourself on the back and do your mental high fives (I always do those, they're cool), have a look at the factor you just created and open the "Advanced Settings" accordion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="advanced tab" src="/img/advanced-tab-counted.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay attention to the "Count user when triggered". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a factor, this is defaulted to "Yes", while on a metric, this is defaulted to "No". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What does all this mean?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a user triggers your factor, that user will be "counted into" your test. That means they will fall into the test and they will be measured by all your metrics you set up in your campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any test, it's important that we count a user at the right point. We want to ensure that &lt;strong&gt;only users who see our change should be counted into the test&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or specifically, &lt;strong&gt;only users who match the trigger of our factor&lt;/strong&gt; will be counted into our test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this example, we don't need to do anything else. When a user triggers the factor, the user will be counted into the test. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all easy. Everybody on the homepage will fall into this test because everybody will see the button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at a slightly more complex test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A slightly more complicated example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next test is on the &lt;strong&gt;delivery options&lt;/strong&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="delivery options page" src="/img/delivery-options-mobile.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this test we want to change the title for the mobile tickets delivery method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replace...
"Skip queues with our mobile app"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With...
"Skip queues with our mobile app (Free!)"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do the same as with our previous test. We create a factor where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trigger:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URL: Your regex to match the delivery options URL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Body: Your regex to match title text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search: Regex for the title text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace: Your replacement title text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a user is triggered and therefore &lt;strong&gt;counted&lt;/strong&gt; into the test when the &lt;strong&gt;trigger&lt;/strong&gt; qualifies them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set up is the same as before. So what's different? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not all users will see the mobile ticket option. Users who don't see the mobile tickets option will &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; be match the trigger and therefore will &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; be counted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So basically, our &lt;strong&gt;counted&lt;/strong&gt; group is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; all users who hit the delivery options page, but instead &lt;strong&gt;only those users who match the trigger criteria&lt;/strong&gt;. i.e. Those who will see mobile tickets as a delivery option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn't so bad. It was a more complex example but we didn't need to do anything different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default settings for the "Count user" on the factor took care of everything for us. We just needed to understand what it was doing and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's look at an even more complicated example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You ready?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An even more complicated example test&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next test idea is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="homepage groupsave" src="/img/homepage-groupsave.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our requirement for this test is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a user makes a search for 3 or more passengers, automatically select groupsave AND display the message on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You got that? Pause for a moment and make sure it's clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to do all of this with javacript, so we create a factor with the following setup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trigger:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URL: Your regex to match the homepage URL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Body: Your regex to match the homepage script block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search: Regex to find the homepage script block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace: Add your great javascript to do everything the test requires&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see the problem here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ALL traffic is going to be triggered into the test because the experiment conditions are met on the client-side.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our test group should only be those users who have made a search for three or more passengers&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the only group who are going to see anything different. Everyone else will see the normal experience and will not be subject to anything in our test. So we don't want them counted into our test. They're just noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask your local analytics person about this, and they will tell you it'd make their lives better if you could only capture the test group for them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well there's two things, you need to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disable the count in the factor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Count users into the test using javascript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Disable the count in the factor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept is simple. We disable count on the factor(s) involved in the test. Great! That's easy. Remember the screenshot I already showed you of where you do that? Here it is again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="advanced tab" src="/img/advanced-tab-counted.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to set that to "no" and save it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now anyone who triggers the factor will &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; be counted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to count someone in via JavaScript. That isn't as difficult as it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Count users into the test using javascript&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should already know how to fire an Event Track metric for SiteSpect to track, but in case you need a refresher:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, use the following script to fire an event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;if(window.SS){SS.EventTrack.rp(&amp;#39;SomeValue&amp;#39;);}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Use that script any way you please, like attach it to a button click event. Replace 'SomeValue' with something specific to your use case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our example, we want to fire an event if a user adds three or more passengers from the dropdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our javascript looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;if (number_of_passengers &amp;gt; 2){
   if(window.SS){SS.EventTrack.rp(&amp;#39;SomeValue&amp;#39;);}
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is a simplistic example of the script. It's there for demonstration purposes only!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If everything is working as it should, then you should see a request being made when this event fires. Check the network tab of your fave browser to see it being fired. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the above example, you'll see something like this...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;/__ssobj/track?event=SomeValue&amp;amp;value=undefined&amp;amp;x=1477109639617-1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So now your script is firing an event. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should know that it's useless without a metric to &lt;strong&gt;catch&lt;/strong&gt; the event. Your metric for this will have the following triggers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="metric event track" src="/img/ss-metric-event.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you want to &lt;strong&gt;count&lt;/strong&gt; someone using that metric, just open the same Advance settings that exist for the factor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="advanced tab" src="/img/advanced-tab-counted.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And set that to "yes".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There you have it. You've disabled the count on the factor and you've enabled a count on a metric! Easy, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rules and regulations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quick note about being 100% transparent when you're doing things like this. Otherwise it can get confusing for you when it comes to re-using factors and metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Naming convention&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you set a factor to NOT COUNT, append "[NOT COUNTED]" to the end of the name of that factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you set a metric to COUNT, append "[COUNTED]" to the end of the name of that metric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, when you review your test build it's obvious that you've made some fundamental changes to how things have been set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are pretty major changes, so you want to be as transparent about it as possible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Put your event-fire javascripts inside a Campaign Variation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want your javascript event track to fire for both the variation AND the control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So put your event-fire javascripts into a campaign variation. That way it's available to all the variations in that campaign, including your control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script will also fire in the same way for all variations, so you can better compare behaviour in your sample groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Fire an event to DTM to let Adobe know when you've triggered someone into a test&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't leave Adobe out in the cold! We need to let Adobe know when you're triggering someone into a test using javascript. I've already created a function to do much of the work, so all you need to do is send the function the campaign and variation group ID to add.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do this with the following script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;assign_to_adobe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;__SS_LISTCAMPAIGN{__SS_TCID__:__SS_VGID__}{;}__&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you add this to your campaign variation, SiteSpect will automatically add the Campaign ID and Variation Group ID to the script. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for our example, the final script in our campaign variation is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;number_of_passengers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class="n"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;SS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;SS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;EventTrack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;SomeValue&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);}&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class="nt"&gt;assign_to_adobe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;__SS_LISTCAMPAIGN{__SS_TCID__:__SS_VGID__}{;}__&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We're using DTM, and have a custom event set up to look out for an event like that. The ID's are sent over to DTM, which then attaches the details to an Adobe list variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Adobe and SiteSpect should be working in perfect harmony together!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal Ali</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:,2016-10-05:2016/counting-users-into-an-experiment</guid><category>traffic-assignment</category><category>test-build</category><category>counting</category></item><item><title>Previewing multiple campaign variations</title><link>/2016/preview-multiple-campaigns</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This post will describe how to preview a multiple campaign variations. So you can check what the combination of tests looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What you need to get started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all you need to install the necessary plugins for your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/modify-headers-for-google/innpjfdalfhpcoinfnehdnbkglpmogdi?hl=en-US"&gt;Modify Header for Google Chrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-us/firefox/addon/modify-headers/"&gt;Modify Header for Firefox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add a section as per the image below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="modify headers setting" src="/img/modify-headers-settings.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. ACTION&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. NAME:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; X-SiteSpect-Preview
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;3. VALUE EXAMPLE:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; { &amp;quot;VG_IDs&amp;quot;: [ &amp;quot;101&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;121&amp;quot; ] }
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(this places the user into a preview session that includes variation groups 101 and 121)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm assuming you know where the campaign Variation Group ID's can be found. Note: Campaign ID's are NOT needed since the campaign variation group ID's are unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. DESCRIPTION&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Multiple Preview
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;5. TURN IT ON!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hit the green play button on the top of the screen to turn on the header.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="modify headers setting" src="/img/modify-headers-settings-switch.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And also hit the "on" icon on the row to "activate" the header modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="modify headers setting" src="/img/modify-headers-settings-on-off-toggle.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. PREVIEW&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll need to then use a preview link for all of this to take effect. The preview link is simply this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.domain.com/?SS_PREVIEW_EXP=2013_NOV_30_1300GMT (the value is a date that needs to be a future date)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for Trainline, a preview link is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thetrainline.com/?SS_PREVIEW_EXP=2090_NOV_30_1300GMT]"&gt;https://www.thetrainline.com/?SS_PREVIEW_EXP=2090_NOV_30_1300GMT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal Ali</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:,2016-10-05:2016/preview-multiple-campaigns</guid><category>previews</category><category>qa</category></item><item><title>The power of the hypothesis in A/B testing</title><link>/2016/the-power-of-the-hypothesis-in-ab-testing</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When it comes to A/B testing, we've found the hypothesis to be an essential part of our process. It works by helping us keep focus on the reason we're testing. It's basically the heart that powers an idea through to completion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is it about this statement that makes it so invaluable? And how specifically has it helped us? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I answer these questions, let's look at an example hypothesis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"On the product listings page, presenting users with more information about each product will improve clarity and confidence, therefore increasing overall conversion."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement does a number of things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It tells us what we want to change (and the page we want to apply the change to)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That two variables are related, namely the displaying of product information and the conversion rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How and why we think there is a relationship between the two variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now want to create an experiment to prove this hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, I have to point out that the hypothesis above was created for the sole purpose of this article. I'll be referring to it throughout the rest of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How the hypothesis validates itself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any hypothesis, it's essential that we interrogate it properly, cross-referencing it with as many other sources of information as possible. This includes looking at past tests, any user feedback we've received, as well as any supporting data from our analytics package. We're looking for clues that suggest the assumptions might be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We note that the test idea centres "on the product listings page". This means we'll want to know what the drop-off rate for this page is, as well as the traffic volume -- the more traffic a given page has, the better as it means a test will stand a better chance of reaching statistical significance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also note that we've justified the relationship between our two variables (remember the two variables are: viewing product details and the conversion rate). This relationship is suggested with the "...will improve clarity and confidence..." part of the statement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justifying how the two variables are related helps us "buy" the statement. Without that justification, it might be difficult to see how and why such a relationship could exist. It would feel too much like of a leap in logic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The hypothesis keeps our focus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest strength of the hypothesis is it's ability to keep us focused. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When prioritising our backlog of tests, the hypothesis keeps conversations relevant, to the point, and specific to the assumptions being made. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also allows us to check other ideas that might be similar! We can then either combine those tests into one, or just plan a test launch order for them (perhaps starting with the simplest test that will give us some validation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When going through the design stages, there is a risk for the scope of the test to balloon. Maybe we get tempted to change more than initially intended, especially when we research other sites and the cool ways they tackle the design challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To stop us from becoming too ambitious with the solution to our problem, we often find the need to take a step back and lean on our hypothesis again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This involves looking at what we're trying to prove and ensuring we've not lost our way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a hypothesis that hasn't proven itself before, we may decide to do the least amount of work in order to prove or disprove it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, for a hypothesis that &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; proven itself, we may decide it’s okay to be a little more ambitious. Either way, it’s a decision we can only be make after referring back to that core statement of ours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ensuring our test can answer the question we're asking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to ensure that anything we build is designed in such a way that it answers the questions raised by our hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may mean deciding on how many variations we’re going to need. For example, if we've made a number of changes, are we controlling for them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It often helps check for the possible outcomes we might face, and then ensure we'll have a good chance of understanding why certain results happened. Remember, our hypothesis is that users seeing the product details will end up converting in higher numbers. We need to ensure we can prove this relationship! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s remind ourselves of the hypothesis again...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"On the product listings page, presenting users with more information about each product will improve clarity and confidence, therefore increasing overall conversion."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...and focus on the part of the sentence: "presenting users with more information about each product ... increasing overall conversion". As stated previously, these are the two variables that we think are related, so we definitely know we want to try and measure those two at least!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that the final implementation of our test involves an accordion, sliding down to reveal the extra information. Clicking on the accordion will show or hide that information. That means we'll need to track clicks to the expand/collapse component as it's the closest we have to proving that a user has seen the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also goes without saying that we'll also want to track our overall conversion rate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Checking if the hypothesis is validated&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all has gone well, weeks later, we should have a concluded test to analyse. Much time may have elapsed since the formation of that idea, so the hypothesis will act as a reference point for the analyst so that she knows what she’s looking for during analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the possible outcomes of the test:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hypothesis validated (Win!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hypothesis invalidated (Lose!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hypothesis inconclusive (Not sure!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the test is successful, we may have uncovered an area to concentrate on for future tests. We can therefore create new hypotheses to investigate things further. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an unsuccessful or inconclusive test, we may still find we've learned something. So it's not all bad! Perhaps we proved that there may not be a relationship between our two variables after all. Or maybe we’ve uncovered a new friction point. Like inconsistent messaging or something, meaning we might want to revise the test conditions and try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, win or lose, the findings of this test should lead to more hypotheses, and this will in turn deliver us with a new set of test statements to validate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Iqbal Ali</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:,2016-10-05:2016/the-power-of-the-hypothesis-in-ab-testing</guid><category>optimisation</category></item></channel></rss>
>>>>>>> 51cd5d4a8eaa6db290b02adaf00cc5ac16805543
